Boycotts, anti-booing technology, and
accusations of voter manipulation. This
Saturday, the Eurovision Song Contest
will take place in Vienna, with 35
countries competing in a spectacle of
song and dance broadcast across the
continent and beyond. But this year will
be different. Five countries, Ireland,
Spain, the Netherlands, Iceland, and
Slovenia have opted to boycott the
contest in protest at the continued
participation of Israel. Irish
broadcaster RTE described participating
as unconscionable given the appalling
loss of lives in Gaza and the
humanitarian crisis there. I've come to
York to chat to Dr. Catherine Baker,
lecturer in 20th century history at the
University of Hull. I asked her all
about how Eurovision came to be such a
lightning rod for international tensions
and how states like Israel, but also
others, use mega events like Eurovision
to project a certain version of
themselves to the rest of the world.
This year, Eurovision is facing the
[music] biggest and coordinated boycott,
at least since 1970, maybe in its
history. I don't know how you would
mark the kind of how big this particular
boycott is. Can you explain a little bit
about what's going on this year?
Certainly. So, we're now in the the
third year in a row where the contest
has been very much overshadowed by
controversies over whether the Israeli
broadcaster should take part. And, you
know, that began in the first months of
Israel's war on Gaza, which followed,
of course, Hamas's 7th October terror
attack on Israel.
>> And so, there are five countries, I
think I'm right in saying that have
either pulled out from competing or from
broadcasting altogether. Is that
correct?
>> Correct. So, there are five broadcasters
who won't be taking part in in
Eurovision this year. And, you know,
each of them has a a long and
distinguished record in the contest in
various ways. So, this is the
broadcasters of Spain, Slovenia,
Iceland, Ireland, and the Netherlands.
Yeah, so I guess one of the um kind of
uh parts of how Eurovision works in
there is that you talk about the the
broadcasters
because it is uh sort of the way in
which um Eurovision works is that it is
a sort of consortium of broadcasters, is
that correct? Well, this is really one
of the big tensions of Eurovision. So,
on the one hand, it is
organized by the what's essentially
Europe's association of public service
broadcasters. So, you know, broadcasters
like the the BBC, which have a a public
service remit, and, you know, are more
than purely commercial entities. So, you
know, every every country has at least
one public service broadcaster in
Europe. Those are joined together in the
European Broadcasting Union, and, you
know, that's an organization which does
all kinds of different things with its
members. It sort of supports them to
exchange technological best practice.
It speaks up for the interest of public
service broadcasting towards governments
and at European level. And as an
offshoot of what it does, which is also
the main reason anyone in the public has
heard of it, if it they've heard of it
at all, is it organizes the Eurovision
Song Contest. And it's been doing that
since 1956.
So, technically, the competitors are
broadcasters.
And yet national representation is so
baked into the structure of Eurovision.
So, you know, it's an international
competition. When you watch it, you see
country names everywhere, you see flags
everywhere. It wouldn't necessarily have
to be like that. You know, if you
picture um international music festival,
you know, there's bands from dozens of
countries potentially, but they're not
all waving their flags all the time.
But, you know, Eurovision has this
international
competition structure, you know, like
the Olympics, like a World Cup. And, you
know, arguably that's been a a big part
of the the spectacle and why people
enjoy watching it. But, what it means
is, you know, you can't separate the the
national representation from the the
Eurovision format. Yeah, there's almost
like an alternative version where we're
cheering on the BBC's entry rather than
the the UK's entry, I guess. And but the
the the five countries that
are boycotting this year, I was
interested this is something that I
hadn't sort of realized, I guess,
sort of being aware of Eurovision
through the BBC, I guess, was that the
five broadcasters that have pulled out,
there'd already been quite a lot of
tension there between them and the
European Broadcasting Union that
organizes it.
>> Absolutely, yes. So, I mean, this is a
story which goes back at least three
years now, and, you know, arguably even
further than that, I think, especially
with Iceland. So, the
the contest in
was in particularly difficult
circumstances. The artists who had
signed up for it entered their national
selection processes
during the summer of 2023. So, you know,
they had no idea what the the
geopolitical situation was going to be
like.
And, you know, this was also coming off
the back of, you know, what had been an
extremely successful contest in 2023.
So, you might remember the BBC in
Liverpool were hosting that on Ukraine's
behalf.
Ukraine had won the 2022 contest, and
the European Broadcasting Union then had
to conclude that
the contest could not be safely and
securely held in Ukraine because of
Russia's full-scale invasion.
So, they offered the contest for
runner-up, that was the BBC, and the the
BBC and, you know, their their partners
in the host city
essentially staged what was a a
co-production between UK and Ukrainian
partners.
And, you know, you usually in Eurovision
have, you know, quite a lot of nation
banding on behalf of the host country.
What you had with 2023 was you know very
much about UK-Ukrainian partnership and
you know a lot of opportunities has
built in for the the Ukrainian partners
to be able to showcase their culture and
within the limits of
Eurovision's rules against political
messages
which you know could be perhaps more
fluid in some cases than others you know
be able to communicate the kinds of
narratives you know existentially
important
you know for the Ukrainian partners to
communicate to international public.
Yeah thank you and we would we'll
certainly talk about Ukraine Ukraine and
Russia again
in a moment because I think that's a
really interesting comparison that I
think a lot of people involved in
boycotts or kind of watching have sort
of maybe brought up in in relation to
the example of Israel which is sort of
the the the main focus of the boycott
this year and there was also some sort
of quite specific
contest related almost conduct matters
which have have sort of influenced the
boycott as well and around one of the
tensions was around sort of anti-booing
technology last year but also around
kind of
maybe I'll say sort of like alleged
voter
manipulation.
>> Yes I mean the question about vote
manipulation became a scandal in 2025
but you know already perhaps was brewing
in 2024. What I think affected a a lot
of the broadcasters stances for ones
which have been you know particularly
pressuring the EBU was essentially how
the backstage atmosphere was managed in
Malmö which was the
the host city in 2024. A number of the
artists who were taking part in Malmö
with Palestinians
and you know this was
especially coming off the back of 2023
you had I think almost a quarter of the
artists were LGBTQ plus of some
description. You had the the first two
non-binary contestants, and
the the highest the highest profile the
highest profile of these artists was
Olly Alexander as well, who you might
remember. And
you know, he because of his profile, he
did come in for you know, particular
pressure from activists in his own
community wanting him to boycott. And
you know, by that time each one of these
artists was under some kind of
contractual obligation or another. I
think we don't actually know what the
consequences would have been if any of
those artists had not performed. But you
know, you can imagine that they were in
a
each one of them was in a very difficult
sort of personal situation, and you
know, within their own communities. And
you know, there had just been a year
where Eurovision had shown itself, you
know, able to
stand on the side of a
community that was facing
full-scale invasion, you know, by an
aggressor state that wanted to erase its
culture. Each of the artists who wanted
to express dissent, you know, then had
to negotiate the
contest organizers' rules. And you know,
artists were trying to, you know, make
gestures of solidarity that
they thought might still be permissible.
And you know, then were being told that
they had broken the rules that they
couldn't do something. And at the same
time, the artists who were more vocally
pro-Palestine
also were reporting intrusive behavior
from some delegation members with the
Israeli broadcaster.
And they reported that and felt that
nothing was being done.
And
you know, the Irish contestant Bambie
Thug, for instance, actually missed one
of their rehearsals to put in a put in a
complaint about it. Who's actually got a
horrible experience to be there but it
sounds like it. And you know from from a
different kind of perspective it was a
you know it was an upsetting experience
for some of the contestants. You know
given the
you know the intense security measures
that she had you know that she had to go
around under. So you know there was a a
very charged heated atmosphere
backstage. News was sort of coming out
to
to the contestants, to other people
backstage. It was coming out through fan
media. So you know this
entire distributed digital community who
follow it who follows Eurovision
was wondering why artists hadn't turned
up to rehearsals. And what what is the
atmosphere I guess this year in that as
you say there is a huge community that
kind of exists around this contest and
and throughout the year as well as just
um around the the the date of the
contest itself. Um what is the the the
feeling there? My my sense is that there
are a lot of people are really quite
split cuz I mean as as you said for like
that it's very politicized um community
in some ways.
>> There's a lot of people who are really
sort of renegotiating what their
attachments to you know this this event
that's brought them you know so much joy
and celebration the past has been. Um
I mean you could you could think of it
think of it maybe as you know there are
going to be some people for whom it's
the same as
you know the way the way that many Harry
Potter fans have
completely reevaluated what that that
franchise means to them. Um
You know after the kind of public
positions that J.K. Rowling has ended
has ended up taking.
You know which for them completely
conflict with the values that drew them
to drew them to that franchise in the
first place.
And
perhaps because you know Eurovision for
so long you know really did manage to
present itself as you know somewhere
that was a
a safe haven from the
anti-LGBTQ+ anti-trans politics that
have just been growing and growing.
And, you know, Conchita Wurst was the
big icon, you know, when she won in
2014.
And, you know, that actually drew so you
know, so many more queer artists to what
towards Eurovision. There was an entire
kind of post-Conchita generation. If you
look at someone like Nemo who won in
2024, JJ who won in 2025, um
Nemo's Swiss, Jager's Austrian. People
who growing up were watching Conchita
and, you know,
became you know, became attached to
Eurovision as
a place where that kind of, you know,
representation of
being queer and being from a nation
at the same time could just completely
go together. It is, you know, that very
generation in some cases who, you know,
are now at the forefront of rethinking
what does this event mean to
So, Nemo for instance actually returned
their trophy last year after the
the EBU General Assembly adopted reforms
which meant Israel's broadcaster would
participate this year. Yeah, I I was
interested um
doing this sort of prep for this. Um I
don't think I'd really tapped into this
this issue around the the voting last
year where um there's a lot of upset
alongside this kind of broader more
foundational um upset everything that's
happening in Gaza and then Israel's
continued participation, but also this
specific um
issue around the the government sort of
like encouraging
uh people sort of supporters in other
countries to vote for them. Can you
explain a little bit about that
controversy to me? So, the voting the
voting for the grand final is made up
50%
the
drewers of music professionals and 50
50% of the public vote.
So, what we're talking about here
particularly concerns the public vote.
So,
you know, the the Eurovision voting
scandals in the past have, you know,
have often involved drawers, but this is
a a public one.
And essentially what happened in 2025
was that um
Israeli government advertising agency
was found to have
booked
a lot of targeted advertising
encouraging supporters to vote for the
Israeli entry the maximum number of
times.
So, Eurovision's voting platform
at actually allowed
users to vote up to 20 times per payment
method. The average person watching
Eurovision might or might not vote.
They might just vote for one song. They
might vote for sort of two or three
favorites. Very few people probably even
know that you can vote or that you could
vote rather up to 20 times. That's been
changed to 10 as part of the the reform
the reform package for 2026.
So,
you know, you can imagine that
potentially, especially in, you know,
smaller countries, perhaps, you know, if
there is a
coordinated
effort to get supporters of one song
to vote that maximum 20 20 number of
times, then
potentially that could inflate the vote
beyond what the the broadcasters who
disagreed with this considered fair.
And, you know, we
you know, we we we need we need to be
really careful, I think, how we how we
talk about this because
we need Okay, we we need to be very
aware of how many anti-Semitic
conspiracy theories there are. So, you
know, we we need to go on the basis of
you know, what you know, what has been
established and documented. On top of
the the wider
context, you know, there was this sort
of
immediate issue.
And the reason why I think that then
became,
you know, something that gave
broadcasters
who were dissenting with Israel's
participation more leverage,
is, you know, this was now something
that was very much within the EBU's
control. In order to be able to have any
kind of international cultural
cooperation, there needs to be trust,
and you know,
especially when you're talking about a a
competition, which Eurovision is. You
know, if you don't have that baseline
level of trust,
you know, cultural activity just is not
going to happen. And, you know, that's
when what That's when what we saw broke
down.
And, you know, a number of broadcasters
were
really doubting whether the votes that
Israel had received in their countries
were completely organic,
given the kinds of patterns that they
were used to in the past. To some people
it might seem, uh,
odd for a country to, um,
care so much about how well they do in,
um, you know, what we could derogatorily
see as like a a singing contest, right?
Why Why is it so important for Israel in
particular, or for for another country
that finds themselves in a situation
where they really want to, um,
be participating and to be doing well
within a sort of broader geopolitical
context? Why is it seem to seem to
matter so much?
I think there's many countries where,
you know, Eurovision really stands out
for its public diplomacy value.
And,
you know, that's
not something perhaps that UK viewers
are maybe maybe as used to,
because the UK is already a country with
a very strong international image.
But, you know,
if you are from a country on, you know,
one of one of Europe's peripheries,
and, you know, the international image
of your country is not very well known
or unclear or
people don't even really understand what
makes your country different from its
neighbors,
you know, then a platform to be able to
communicate, you know, your culture,
your language often, you know, on terms
which are, you know, developed by a
creative team of yours, really is quite
significant. Ever since the turn of the
millennium,
you know, there was also a kind of
direct nation branding value that it
would have,
you know, if you were a country that
was, you know, going through the EU
accession process because, you know,
this was when the the EU's big big
enlargement into into Central and
Ea- Ea- Eastern Europe
w- was going on.
And, you know, being able to show that
you could actually deliver, you know, a
a Eurovision production or, you know,
even better, if you win it and then host
it, you know, being able to show that
you can deliver that to,
you know, world-class standards,
really was quite an important message.
>> I suppose also a way to show yourself as
part of Europe, right?
>> Absolutely, yes. Yeah. And, you know,
whether there was that cultural anxiety
that's come from the the ways in which,
you know, the
peripheries of Europe which have so
often been marginalized by Europe's
Europe's northwest, you know, there was
a really strong desire to be recognized
as European. I mean, I think we felt
that in the UK maybe post Iraq war,
maybe post um
Brexit, there were times where we
suddenly didn't do very well for a very
long time. Um maybe up until um the year
we came the we the we came second. One
of the terms that's been used around uh
Israel's participation, I guess
particularly, has been this notion of of
art washing. Can you tell me a little
bit about about that, please? Okay, so
yes, art washing is the idea that a
a state committing human rights abuses
can try to launder its international
image, essentially,
by if we're talking about artwashing,
you know, sponsoring the arts and
culture. So, you know, there's
a lot of ways in which this general idea
gets talked about. So, you know, you
might have heard of sportswashing, for
instance, and you know, that's the the
same argument with sporting events. So,
you know, hosting hosting the World Cup,
hosting the Olympics.
And authoritarian regimes can do it,
democracies can do it, as well. So,
you know, it is
>> [sighs]
>> thought to be
a a good public diplomacy move
if there's something that you don't want
the world to notice about what you're
doing, host a mega event. Presumably,
the demand, I guess, on the part of the
countries that have pulled out this year
is that
Israel is
expelled, I don't know what the exact
term would be,
but there is some sort of context to
that, or
what's the word, a kind of previous
example of that in what happened with
Russia in 2022.
Is that correct? Or that was a little
bit different, am I right in saying?
That was quite a different situation,
and one of the reasons I think it
was different is the foreign policy side
of it.
So, you might remember that in
Russia's full-scale invasion began on
the 24th of February, and within 48
hours, the EBU had decided that Russian
broadcasters
would not take part in Eurovision 2022.
And
what happened in those intervening 48
hours
is very initially, the EBU appeared to
state that Russia would continue as
usual,
and immediately, the public broadcaster
of Ukraine said that it wouldn't
participate if that was the case.
And then, around nine other broadcasters
from various Baltic, Nordic, Central
European countries joined it as well.
So, you know, you would then have had
>> A very diminished contest.
>> Exactly, exactly, yes. And
the EBU then changed course
and said that the Russian entry wouldn't
participate, which hadn't hadn't
actually been been selected at that
time. And what had happened is
internationally in the meantime is, you
know, European institutions and many,
many national governments had come up
with their sanctions packages. So, you
know, there was a
a very clear political stir. And, you
know, there was also a very clear
consensus about, you know, how
>> [sighs]
>> Russia was going to be treated in
international politics. And so, is the
treatment of the two different
countries, is that
is that largely just around the very
different geopolitical contexts around
them? There was no consensus within the
EBU, you know, or outside it in the
European public sphere
about what the situation with
Israeli interests participating in
international events should be at this
point. So, you know, you were talking
earlier about how important it is to
to Khan and to Israeli political leaders
that is also represented.
But, you know, there are also several
broadcasters to whom it is as important
that Israel does participate, you know,
because of the the foreign policy and,
you know, the memory politics in the
countries they come from. You know, so
with you know, with Germany for
instance, the same way that, you know,
German German politicians have very very
much stood unconditionally with Israel
in the international arena. And, you
know, linked that to
something existential for modern-day
Germany, given, of course, the history
history that Germany has. So,
likewise, you know, Germany's public
broadcaster, Austria's public
broadcaster, are
very, very adamant that
the EBU needs to do everything it can to
keep Israel's broadcaster participating.
So,
you know, if that vote in December had
gone the other way, you might have seen
withdrawals by
by broadcasters protesting that Israel
wasn't there. And the EBU broadly um
stands by its view that the contest is
not political, I guess. Um how do they
sort of justify that view in a world
where um I mean, you you've talked um
just then about um
uh not only the expulsion of Russia, but
also, you know, um
the UK coming second, Ukraine coming
first, and that kind of experience of
the contest sort of very much wrapping
itself around um Ukraine, the the slogan
for the um contest changed, and and
there was this real kind of
positive use of the contest as a sort of
statement of European uh unity, I guess,
against um at least partly against
Russian aggression. Um how does the EP
EBU
sort of
justify that now it's sort of being
apolitical? I think that's the question
that the EBU itself is still trying to
work out. So,
the contest current director, who is
Martin Green, who was in charge of the
ceremonies for the
Birmingham 2022 Commonwealth Games, he
was in charge of
the He was head of ceremonies for the
London 2012 Olympics. He was in charge
of
Hull City of Culture in 2017. But there
was a phrase that he likes to use of
Eurovision which is essentially the
world as it could be, not necessarily as
it is. So,
it's the force that, you know, sort of
through cooperating on staging
a
a cultural event
in what is a very contentious public
sphere outside it, you know, that it's
possible to
model some kind of
dialogue and intercultural understanding
that
even if it doesn't exist outside the
contest ought to exist within that space
in which it's being produced and
enjoyed. And, you know, if you read that
in another way, it's asking people to
leave their politics at the door. It's
either a utopian view from one angle or
a sort of naive view depending on where
you're coming at that from, I guess. It
is. Yeah, and you know, I think
especially after, you know, what artists
who wanted to express themselves
politically went through in 2024,
you know, there are
probably going to be artists who 5 years
ago would have been very, very excited
to
take part in Eurovision
who
in this moment are not going to be
prepared to
make the compromises. The grand final
always opens with a flag parade and it's
done that ever since the the previous
normal contest in 2013.
And for a
a few years in the early 2020s, artists
were able to bring
another flag that expressed something of
their identity as well as their national
one. So, you know, when Nemo went out in
their flag parade, you know, they had a
non-binary flag as well as a Swiss one.
The Italian artist the the year before
that had a a pride flag as well as his
Italian one, and you know, at a time
when LGBT plus rights were being rolled
back by the Italian government.
The The Icelandic band Via before that
had
been able to bring a big trans flag as
well as the Icelandic flag. So, you
know, you'd got these
very symbolic sort of moments. Um
Australian artists quite often brought
an indigenous Australian flag along with
the Australian state flag. And then for
2025, it was announced that artists
could only have their national flag
on air. So, you know, no more pride
flags essentially
in the flag parade or in the green room,
you know, where artists sit wait waiting
for the results. And
>> clamping down of one form of political
expression has spread out to other forms
of expression um in in the contest as
well. It has. I mean, you know, you
know, the organizers would say that you
know, they are
LGBT plus culture is still being
represented in the contest in other
ways. And, you know, Nemo for instance
in the interval of the grand final in
2025 gave a, you know, a very raw
emotive performance of a
a new song of theirs about the the modus
operandi of being non-binary. But, you
know, certainly the
the fact that they did take away,
you know, that very
symbolic way of, you know, expressing
these these multiple identities together
did not go down particularly well. Do
you think there is a path back to that
place where maybe maybe this is
rose-tinted glasses that I'm that I'm
reading from what you said, but that
that kind of moment where it did feel
like Eurovision sort of could be a kind
of uniting force within
Europe. Do you think there's a path back
there, or do you think
some of these divisions have run through
Europe outside of Eurovision too much to
to to make that possible?
>> I think it would need to go through some
radical transformations
essentially. And
you know, I think one thing that
many people are probably more conscious
of now than they were a few years ago
is
you know, the fact that
you know, there was no Palestinian
representation for instance at
Eurovision. And you know, the the reason
for that is
essentially, you know,
there is a broadcast in Palestine in the
occupied West Bank, but it doesn't meet
the criteria for EBU membership. It's
not politically independent. So, there
was actually a campaign in in 2000 in
2007 by a Palestinian music NGO to get a
a Palestinian entry into Eurovision.
And it didn't come to anything, but you
know, it shows that
back then, you know, there was some
interest in engaging with it. The only
Palestinian representation that's going
to come through through Eurovision, you
know, is going you know, is going to be
through the diaspora for instance. And
you know, it's going to be happening now
in a
a context where
you know, anyone of Palestinian heritage
who wants to express that
is feeling that
their expression of their heritage is
politicized
in a way that others expressions of
their heritage is not. And you know,
Eurovision is an event, you know, which
has traded for years and years and years
on
you know, artists being able to do
creative things, you know, with the the
heritage and culture of their their
ethnic background.
And now it feels like it's denying that.
Um well, thank you so thank you so much.
Um that's been so enlightening. Um and
I'm I'm sure everyone that's watching it
will be um give so much context to um
some of the sort of headlines that will
be happening uh happening this weekend.
So, thank you so much, Katherine. Thank
you so much for watching what is a
pretty timely video for this channel.
Usually, we work on a much sort of
longer scale of things being relevant,
but that's something we're trying to do
a little bit more of. It's something
we're particularly doing over on my new
project, Slow News Day. Some of you for
a while have enjoyed videos that have
been on a channel which has previously
been known as Tom Nicholas too. Uh but
we've decided to completely revamp and
rebrand that as a new thing called Slow
News Day, which is an almost daily news
update show broadcasting four times a
week in which each day I take a topic
which is trending in the news and try
and provide a little bit of context and
clarity to that. If you watch it here on
YouTube, you'll be able to watch two
episodes of that every single week.
However, if you want to watch all four
episodes of Slow News Day, you will have
to go over to Nebula. Uh if you watch my
stuff, uh you will already be more than
aware of Nebula. It is the premium
streaming service put together by myself
and a bunch of other inquisitive
creators. Some of those being
news-related people, some of those video
essayists, some of the kind of cultural
theorists of a type. Um and it is a
premium streaming service which first
and foremost allows you to watch all of
the stuff we put together ad and
sponsor-free, but then also is
increasingly home to a growing amount of
exclusive films and shows as well. That
includes uh Slow News Day, which as I've
said, you get twice as much of if you
are signed up to Nebula, but also
includes a bunch of other stuff. My film
Boomers is on there, for example, but
also stuff like uh Lindsay Ellis, who
has been putting less stuff out here on
YouTube, has been putting out loads of
exclusive stuff over on Nebula. Such as,
for example, her um recent piece about
body cam YouTube, diving into the
cultural politics of this strange genre
of YouTube in which people piece
together uh body cam footage. It is a
fascinating look at the ethics of this
kind of evolution of the true crime
genre. Um Nebula is usually uh £6 a
month, and then you can get a annual uh
subscription, which brings it down to
the equivalent of £5 a month. However,
if you use my link
go.nebula.tv/tomnicholas,
you can slash that in half once again
and get 50% off, bringing it to an
equivalent of £2.50 every month. You can
also, if you would like, get a lifetime
subscription uh if you don't want to add
another uh monthly payment to your bill.
Those are a little bit more expensive,
but get you access to Nebula for as long
as both you and the platform exist, and
have proven really, really popular.
Watching my stuff over on Nebula really
does help to support what we do. We get
paid more when you watch stuff over on
Nebula rather than on YouTube. Um we
also get a little kickback when you sign
up using that uh that link uh
go.nebula.tv/tomnicholas.
So, I would be super duper grateful if
uh you do go over and sign up if you do
use that link. Thank you so much for
watching once again, and I'll see you
over on Nebula.